Ameena Bibi Abdul

Java Full Stack Developer

+1(901) 338-4777 | ameenaabdul2930@gmail.com | Memphis, TN

SUMMARY

Java Full Stack Developer with 3 years of experience in designing, developing, and deploying full-stack web applications. Proficient in Java, JavaScript, HTML/CSS, and frameworks and libraries. Experience in front-end and back-end development, database management, and version control. Developed a microservices architecture that improved application performance.

SKILLS

Methodology: SDLC, Agile, Waterfall

Languages: C, Java, Python

Frameworks: Spring MVC, Hibernate, Node.js, React.js, Restful API, SOAP, WebSocket, RabbitMQ, SaaS, Tailwind, Next.js,

Express.js, Angular.js

Web Technologies: HTML5, CSS3, Bootstrap, XML, YAML, JSON, Ajax, jQuery, DOM Manipulation, Redux, TypeScript, JavaScript

IDEs: PyCharm, Jupyter Notebook, Visual Studio Code, IntelliJ

Cloud Technology: Azure, AWS, Docker, Kubernetes **Application Server:** Apache Tomcat, WebSphere

Databases: SQL, MySQL, MongoDB, SQL Server, PostgreSQL

Version Control Tools: Git, Postman, CI/CD, Jenkins, Jira, Webpack, Rally, Junit, Atom

Operating Systems: Linux, Windows, Mac

EXPERIENCE

Java Full Stack Developer, CitiusTech, USA

August 2024 - Present

- Facilitated all phases of the Software development life cycle (SDLC) using Agile Methodology.
- Developed front-end components using React JS and integrated components with backend services to create seamless user experiences.
- Implemented authentication and authorization using Spring Security to secure web applications, reducing security vulnerabilities and enhancing user data protection.
- Integrated PostgreSQL for data storage and retrieval, implementing database migrations and transactions, resulting in a 25% improvement in data retrieval speed and efficiency.

Java Full Stack Developer, Berkshire Hathaway, USA

January 2024 - June 2024

- Experience in working with client-side architecture using Angular JS for UI development to achieve MVC design flow.
- Leveraged AWS Services such as EC2, S3, RDS, and Lambda for deploying and managing cloud-based applications, leading to a reduction in infrastructure costs and an improvement in application scalability and performance.
- Practiced GIT for version control, Maven for building scripts, and configured log4j.

Java Full Stack Developer, Experion Technologies, INDIA

May 2020 - June 2022

- Built server-side applications interacting with databases employing Spring Boot and Hibernate, directly leading to a decrease in data retrieval times.
- Led project planning and coordinated web-based project management tasks with HTML, CSS, JavaScript, and React-optimized website performance, resulting in an increase in user retention and a rise in conversion rates.
- Configured Hibernate configuration files to persist data to the MongoDB database, reducing data processing time and improving database query efficiency.
- Experienced in using Jenkins in code deployment and migrating stored procedures from SQL to MySQL, resulting in a reduction in time for deployment and an improvement in database performance.
- Expertise in deploying applications on Amazon Web Service (AWS), such as building, testing, and deploying Identity
 Microservices, leading to an increase in the scalability and reliability of applications.
- Experience in integrating Ansible into CI/CD pipelines to automate the build, test, and deployment processes, reducing manual intervention and improving overall efficiency.
- Incorporated Model-View-Controller pattern to implement microservices for user authentication RESTful API's. With the help of Spring Boot, accelerated the development of API's by joining the team.

EDUCATION

Masters in Computer Science, University of Memphis, TN

Bachelors, Vignan's Lara Institute of Technology and Sciences, Vadlamudi, AP, India

August 2022 - May 2024

June 2018 - May 2022

CERTIFICATIONS

Introduction to HTML, CSS, & JavaScript IBM and offered through Coursera Exposys Data Labs Certificate of Internship on Data Science